<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The mystery of iniquity working in the dividing of Protestants, in order to the subverting of religion and our laws for almost the space of 30 years last past, plainly laid open with some advices to Protestants of all perswasions in the present juncture of our affairs : to which is added A specimen of a bill for uniting of Protestants / by a Protestant and a true English-man.</title>
            <author>Protestant and true English-man.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 108 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51682</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M3186</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1551</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12265129</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12265129</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58012</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51682)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58012)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 872:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The mystery of iniquity working in the dividing of Protestants, in order to the subverting of religion and our laws for almost the space of 30 years last past, plainly laid open with some advices to Protestants of all perswasions in the present juncture of our affairs : to which is added A specimen of a bill for uniting of Protestants / by a Protestant and a true English-man.</title>
                  <author>Protestant and true English-man.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Separate caption title page: "A specimen of a bill for uniting Protestants ...".</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Protestants --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58012:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity</hi> Working in the dividing of PROTESTANTS, In order to the ſubverting of Religion and our Laws For almoſt the ſpace of 30 Years laſt paſt, plainly laid open.</p>
            <p>With ſome Advices to Proteſtedts of all Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions in the preſent Juncture of our Affairs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To which is ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                     <desc>•••…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> A Specimen a BILL for Un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>g of Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>By a Proteſtant and true Engliſh-man.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Every Kingdom divided againſt it ſelf, is brought to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation; and every City or Houſe divided againſt it ſelf, ſhall not ſtand.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mat. 12.25.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Dum pugnant ſinguli, univerſi vincuntur.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Tacit.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1689.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:58012:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:58012:2"/>
            <head>The Myſtery of Iniquity working in the dividing of Proteſtants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>'TIS long ſince the <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> under the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the <hi>late King</hi> and his <hi>Brother,</hi> was em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bark'd in a deſign of ſubverting the <hi>Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> and of introducing and eſtabliſhing <hi>Popery.</hi> For the two <hi>Royal Brothers</hi> being in the time of their Exile ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by the Careſſes and Importunities of their <hi>Mother,</hi> allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the Promiſes and Favours of Popiſh Princes, and being wheedled by the Crafts and Arts of Prieſts and Jeſuits, who are cunning to deceive, and knew how to prevail upon Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that were but weakly eſtabliſhed in the Doctrine, &amp; wholly ſtrangers to the Practice and Power of the Religion they were tempted from; they not only abjured the Reformed Religion, and became reconciled to the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> but by their Example, and the Influence which they had over thoſe that depended upon them, both for preſent Subſiſtence and future Hopes, they drew many that accompanied them in their Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to renounce the Doctrine, Worſhip, and Communion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> though in the War between <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt and the Parliament, they had pretended to fight for them in equal conjunction with the Prerogatives of the Crown. So that upon the Reſtoration in the Year 1660, they were not only moulded &amp; prepared themſelves for promoting the deſires of the Pope and his Emiſſaries, but they were furniſhed with a ſtock of Gentlemen, out of whom they might have a ſupply of Inſtruments, both in Parliament and elſewhere, to co-ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate with and under them in the Methods that ſhould be judged moſt proper and ſubſervient to the extirpation of Proteſtancy, and the bringing the Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>on again into a Servitude to the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Crown. And beſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>des the Obligations that the Principles
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58012:3"/>of the Religion to which they had revolted, laid them under for eradicating the eſtabliſhed Doctrine and Worſhip, they had bound themſelves unto it, by all the Prom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſes and Oaths which Perſons are capable of having proſcribed unto, and exacted of them.</p>
            <p>Nor can any now disbelieve his late Majeſty's having lived and died a Papiſt, who hath either heard what he both ſaid and did, when under the proſpect of approaching Death, and paſt hope of acting a part any longer on the preſent Stage, or who have ſeen and read the two Papers left in his Cloſet, which have been ſince publiſhed to the World, and atteſted for Authentick by the preſent King. And had we been ſo juſt to our ſelves, as to have examined the whole Courſe of his Reign, both in his Alliances Abroad, and his moſt important Counſels and Actions at Home; or had we hearkned to the Reports of thoſe who knew him at <hi>Collen</hi> and in <hi>Flanders,</hi> we had been long ago con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of what Religion he was. Nor were his many repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Proteſtations of his Zeal for Proteſtancy, but in order to delude the Nation, till inſenſibly as to us, and with ſafety to himſelf, he had overturned the Religion which he pretended to own, and had introduced that which he inveighed againſt. And while with the higheſt aſſeverations he diſclaimed the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what he really was, and with moſt ſacred and tremendous Oaths, profeſſed the being what he was not, his Religion might in the mean time have been traced through all the ſignal Occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences of his Government, and have been diſcerned written in Capital Letters, through all the material Affairs wherein he was engaged, from the Day he aſcended the Throne, till the Hour he left the Work. His entring into two Wars againſt the <hi>Dutch,</hi> without any provocation on their part, or ground on his, ſave their being a Proteſtant State; his being not only conſcious unto, but interpoſing his Commands, as well as En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements, for the burning of <hi>London.</hi> His Concurrence in all the parts of the Popiſh Plot, except that which the Jeſuits, with a few others, were involved in againſt himſelf, his ſtifling that Conſpiracy, and de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ering the Roman Catholicks from the Dangers into which it had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſt them. His being the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of ſo many forged Plots, which he cauſed to be charged on Proteſtants. His conſtant Confede<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>cies with <hi>France,</hi> to the diſobliging his People; the betraying of <hi>Europe;</hi> the neglect of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:58012:3"/>the Reformed in that Kingdom, and the encouraging the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign carried on againſt them for their Extirpation. His en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatling the Duke of <hi>York</hi> upon the Nation, contrary to the Deſires and Endeavours of three ſeveral Parliaments, and that no out of Love to his Perſon, but Affection to Popery, which he knew that Gentleman would introduce and eſtabliſh. All theſe, beſides many other things which might be named, were ſufficient Evidences of the late King's Religion, and of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign he was engaged in for the Subverſion of Ours. So that it would fill a ſober Perſon with amazement, to think, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all this, there ſhould be ſo many ſincere Proteſtants and true Engliſh Men, who not only believed the late King to be of the Reformed Religion, but with an inſatiableneſs thirſted after the Blood of thoſe that durſt otherwiſe repreſent him. And had it not been for his receiving Abſolution and Extream Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction from a Popiſh Prieſt at his Death; and for what he left in writing in the two Papers found in his <hi>ſtrong Box,</hi> he would have ſtill paſſed for a Prince who had lived and died a cordial and zealous Proteſtant, and whoſoever had muttered any thing to the contrary, would have been branded for a Villain and an execrable Perſon. But with what a ſcent and odor muſt it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend his Memory to them, to conſider his having not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lived and died in the Communion of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in contradiction to all his Publick Speeches, ſolemn Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and higheſt Aſſeverations to his People in Parliament; but his participating, from time to time, of the Sacrament as adminiſtred in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> while in the interim he had abjured our Religion, ſtood reconciled to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and had obliged himſelf by moſt ſacred Vows, and was endeavouring, by all the Frauds and Arts imaginable, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the eſtabliſhed Doctrine and Worſhip, and ſet up Hereſy and Idolatry in their room. And it muſt needs give them an abhorrent Idea and Character of Popery, and a loathſom re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation of thoſe truſted with the Conduct and Guidance of the Conſciences of Men in the Roman Communion, that they ſhould not only diſpenſe with and indulge ſuch Crimes and Villanies, but proclaim them Sanctified and Meritorious from the end which they are calculated for and levelled at.</p>
            <p>And for his dear Brother, and renowned Succeſſor, who poſſeſſed the Throne after him, I ſuppoſe his moſt partial Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirers,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58012:4"/>who took him for a Prince, not only merciful in his Temper, and imbued with all gracious Inclinations to our Laws, and the Rights of the Subject, but for one Orthodox in his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and who would prove a zealous Defender of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, Worſhip, and Diſcipline of the Church eſtabliſhed by Law, are before this time both undeceived, and filled with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentments for his having abuſed their Credulity, deceived their Expectations, and reproched all their gloryings and boaſtings of him. For as it would have been the greateſt Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front they could have put upon the King, to queſtion his being of the Roman Communion, or to detract from his Zeal for the introduction of Popery, notwithſtanding his own antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Proteſtations, as well as the many Statutes in force for the preſervation of the Reformed Religion; ſo I muſt take the liberty to tell them, that his Apoſtacy is not of ſo late a Date as the World is made commonly to believe. For though it was many Years concealed, and the contrary pretended and diſſembled; yet it is moſt certain that he abjured the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion, ſoon after the Exilement of the Royal Family, and was reconciled to the Romiſh Church at St. <hi>Germains</hi> in <hi>France.</hi> Nor were ſeveral of the then ſuffering Biſhops and Clergy ignorant of this, though they had neither the Integrity nor Courage to give the Nation and Church warning of it. And within theſe five Years there was in the cuſtody of a very worthy and honeſt Gentleman, a Letter written to the late Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>D.</hi> by a Doctor of Divinity then attending upon the Royal Brothers, wherein the Apoſtacy of the then Duke of York to the Sea of <hi>Rome</hi> is particularly related, and an Account given how much the Dutcheſs of <hi>Tremoville</hi> (who without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her ſelf obſerved) had heard the Queen Mother glorying of it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>alled it as a diſhonour to the Royal Family, and as that which night prove of pernicious Conſequence to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Intereſt. But though the old Queen privately rejoiced and triumphed in it, yet ſhe knew too well what diſadvantage it might be, both to her Son, and to the Papal Cauſe in <hi>Great Britain,</hi> to have it at that Seaſon communicated and divulged. Thereupon it remained a Secret for many Years, and by virtue of a Diſpenſation, he ſometimes joined in all Ordinances with thoſe of the Proteſtant Communion. But for all the Art, Hypocriſy, of and Sacrilege, by which it was endeavoured to be concealed,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58012:4"/>it might have been eaſily diſcerned, as manifeſting it ſelf in the whole Courſe of his Actions. And at laſt his own Zeal, the Importunity of the Prieſts, and the Cunning of the late King, prevailing over Reaſons of State, he withdrew from all Acts of Fellowſhip with the Church of <hi>England.</hi> But neither that, nor his refuſing the <hi>Teſt</hi> enjoined by <hi>Law,</hi> for diſtinguiſhing Papiſts from Proteſtants, though thereupon he was forced, both to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign his Office of Lord High Admiral, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> nor his declining the Oath which the Laws of <hi>Scotland</hi> for the ſecuring a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Governour, enjoin to be taken by the High Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; nor yet ſo many Parliaments having endeavoured to get him excluded from Succeſſion to the Crown, upon the account of having revolted to the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> and thereby become dangerous to the eſtabliſhed Religion, could make impreſſion upon a wilfully deluded and obſtinate ſort of Proteſtants, but in defiance of all means of Conviction, they would perſwade themſelves, that he was ſtill a Zealot for our Religion, and a grand Patriot of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Nor could any thing undeceive them, till upon his Brother's Death he had openly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared himſelf a <hi>Roman Catholick,</hi> and afterwards in the fumes and raptures of his Victory over the late Duke of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> had diſcovered and proclaimed his Intentions of overthrowing both our Religion and Laws. Yea ſo cloſely had ſome ſealed up their Eyes againſt all beams of Light, and hardned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt all Evidences from Reaſon and Fact, that had it pleaſed the Almighty God to have proſpered the Duke of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth</hi>'s Arms in the Summer 85. the preſent King would have gone off the State with the Reputation among them, of a Prince tender of the Laws of the Kingdom; and who, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding his own being a Papiſt, would have preſerved the Reformed Religion, and have maintained the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in all her Grandure and Rights. And tho his whole Life had been but one continued Conſpiracy againſt our Civil Liberties and Priviledges, he had left the Throne with the Character, and under the Eſteem of a Gentleman; that in the whole couſe of his Government would have regulated himſelf by the Rules of the Conſtitution, and the Statutes of the Realm.</p>
            <p>Now among all the Methods fallen upon by the Royal Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, for the undermining and ſubverting our Religion and Laws, there is none that they have purſued with more Ardor,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58012:5"/>and wherein they have been more ſucceſsful to the compaſſing of their Deſigns, than in their dividing Proteſtants, and alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating their Affections, and embittering their Minds from and againſt one another. And had not this lain under their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, and the means of effecting it appeared eaſie, they might have been Papiſts themſelves, while in the mean time they had been diſpenſed with to proteſt and ſwear their being of the Reformed Religion, and they might have envied our Liberties, and bewailed their Reſtriction from Arbitrary and Deſpotical Power; but they never durſt have entertained a Thought of ſubverting the Eſtabliſhed Religion, or of altering the Civil Government, nor would they ever have had the boldneſs to have attempted the introducing and erecting Popery and Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny in their room. And whoſoever ſhould have put them upon reducing the Nation to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or upon rendring the Monarchy unlimited and independent on the Law, would have been thought to have laid a Snare for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing the Papiſts to greater Severities than they were ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious unto before, and to have projected the robbing the Crown of the Prerogatives which belong unto it by the Rules of the Conſtitution, and to which it was ſo lately reſtored. And the deſpair of ſucceeding, would have rendred the Royal Brothers deaf to all Importunities from Romiſh Emiſſaries, and Court Minions. Neither the Promiſes and Oaths which they had made and taken beyond Sea to introduce Popery, nor their Ambition to advance themſelves beyond the reſtraint of Laws, and the Controul of Parliaments, would have prevailed upon them to have encountred the Hazards and Difficulties, which in caſe of the Union of Engliſh Proteſtants, muſt have attended and enſued upon Attempts and Endeavours of the one kind and of the other. Or ſhould their beloved Popery, and their own Bigottedneſs in the Romiſh Superſtition, have ſo far tranſported them beyond the bounds of Wiſdom and Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as to have appeared poſſeſſed with an Intention of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting the Proteſtant Religion, and of enſlaving the Nation to the Superſtition and Idolatry of <hi>Rome,</hi> they would have been made ſoon to underſtand, That the Laws which make it Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to own the Juriſdiction of the Pope, or to ſeduce the meaneſt Subject to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> were not enacted in vain, and that thoſe as well as many more made for the Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:58012:5"/>of the Proteſtant Religion, and to prevent the growth and introduction of Popery, were not to be dallied and plaid withal. Or, ſhould they have been ſo far infatuated and aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned of all Underſtanding, as out of a fooliſh and haughty Affectation of being abſolute, to have attempted the Altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Civil Government, they would have been imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately and unanimouſly told, that the People have the ſame Right to their Liberties, that the King hath to the Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of the Crown. And if they would not have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with what belongs unto the Prince by the Common and Statute Laws of the Realm, but had invaded the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges reſerved unto the Subject: they would have been made to know, that they might not only be withſtood in what they ſtrove to uſurp contrary to <hi>Magna Charta, the Petition of Right,</hi> and other Laws of the Kingdom, but that thereby they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited, and might be diſſeized of what either appertained unto the Crown by fundamental Agreements, or hath been ſince ſettled upon the Monarch by Statute-Laws. Nor could any thing have emboldned his late Majeſty and the preſent King to Enterprizes of the one kind or the other, but the proſpect of begetting a Miſunderſtanding, Jealouſie, and Rancor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Proteſtants, and thereby both of making them inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental to the Ruin of one another, and contributary to the loſs of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Liberty and the Reformed Religion, which they equally value and eſteem, and to the ſetting up Popery and Tyranny, which the one deteſteth and abhorreth no leſs than the other.</p>
            <p>Tho all Engliſh Proteſtants have ever been at an Accord in all the Eſſentials and Vitals of Religion, yet from the very be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the Reformation, there have been Differences among them concerning Eccleſiaſtical Government and Diſcipline, and about Forms, Rites, and Ceremonies of Worſhip. And had they conſulted either their Duty to God, or the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Intereſt of Religion, they might have found ways either for removing the occaſions of them, or they ought to have lived together as Brethren, notwithſtanding the differences which were among them in thoſe things. But how much wiſer are the Children of this World, than thoſe of the Kingdom of God and of Jeſus Chriſt. For tho the differences among the Papiſts do far exceed ours, both in their number and in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:58012:6"/>the importance of thoſe things wherein they diſagree, yet they do mutually tolerate and bear with one another. The matters wherein they differ are neither made the Terms of their Church-Communion, nor the Grounds of mutual Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications and Perſecutions.</p>
            <p>But alas, one Party among us hath been always endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to cut or ſtretch others to their own Size, and have made thoſe things which themſelves ſtile Indifferent, both the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications for admiſſion to the Paſtoral Office, and the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Fellowſhip in the Ordinances of the Goſpel. Nor is it to be expreſſed, what Advantages were hereby adminiſtred all along to the Common Enemy; and what Sufferings peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and orthodox Chriſtians were expoſed unto from their peeviſh and angry Brethren. And though theſe Things, with the Heats begotten among all, and the Calamities undergone by one ſide, were not the cauſe of that funeſtous War betwixt <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt and the <hi>Parliament,</hi> yet they were an occaſion of diverting Thouſands from the ſide which the Perſecuting Church-men eſpouſed, and engaging them in the behalf of the <hi>two Houſes,</hi> in the Quarrel which they begun and carried on againſt that <hi>Prince,</hi> for defence of the Civil Liberties, Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, and Rights of the People. But ſome of the Mitred Clergy were ſo far from being made wiſe by their own and the Nations Sufferings, as upon their Reſtoration to hearken to moderate Counſels, and to decline their former Rigours and Severities, that they became the Tools and Inſtruments of the Court, not only for reviving, but for heightning and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flaming all the Differences which had formerly been among Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Proteſtants. For the Royal Brothers finding nothing more adapted and ſubſervient than this, to their Deſign of altering the Government, and ſubverting Religion, they animated thoſe waſpiſh and impolitick Eccleſiaſticks, not only to purſue the Reſtoration of all thoſe Things which had given Riſe and Occaſion to former Diſſentions and Perſecutions, but to lay new Snares for alienating many Perſons, of unſpotted Lives and tender Conſciences, from the Church, and of rendring them obnoxious to ſuffer in their Names, Perſons, and Eſtates. And what a ſatisfaction was it to the late King and his Brother, to find the old Epiſcopal Clergy prepared through Principles of Revenge, as well as from Love of Domination, Ambition,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:58012:6"/>and Covetouſneſs, to fall in with the Deſign, not only of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing Diviſions among Proteſtants, both by making the Conditions of entring upon the Paſtoral Function narrower, and for ſcrewing Conformity with the Church in her Forms and Ceremonies of Worſhip, into Teſts, for admiſſion to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy and Civil Truſts, but of obtaining ſeveral Laws againſt Diſſenters, whereby the Penalties to which they foreſaw that People would become liable, were rendred greater than they had been before, and their Sufferings made more mercileſs, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humane, and intolerable.</p>
            <p>For though his late Majeſty had, by a Declaration dated at <hi>Breda,</hi> promiſed Indulgence to all Proteſtants that would live peaceably under the Civil Government; yet it was never in his Thoughts to perform it; and the previous Obligations which he was under to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> had a virtue to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſede and cancel his Engagements to Engliſh Hereticks. And all he intended by that Declaration was only to wheedle and lull thoſe into a tameneſs of admitting his return into his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, whom a jealouſy of being afterwards perſecuted for their Conſciences, might have awakened to withſtand and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute it. And, to give him his due, he never judged himſelf longer bound to the obſervation of Promiſes and Oaths made to his People, than, until without hazard to his Perſon and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, he could violate and break them. Accordingly he was no ſooner ſeated in the Throne of his Anceſtors, and thoſe whom he had been apprehenſive of Reſiſtance and Diſturbance from, put out of Capacity and Condition of attempting any thing againſt him; but he thought himſelf diſcharged from every thing that the Royal Word and Faith of a Prince had been pledged and laid to ſtake for in that Declaration, and from that day forward acted in direct oppoſition to all the Parts and Branches of it. For having ſoon after his return obtained a Parliament moulded and adapted, both to his Arbitrary and Popiſh Ends, he immediately ſet all his Inſtruments at work for the procuring ſuch Laws to be enacted, as might divide and weaken Proteſtants, and thereby make us, not only the more eaſy a Prey to the Papiſts, but afford them an advantage through our Scuffles, of undermining our Religion with the leſs notice and obſervation.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:58012:7"/>
            <p>How ſuch Perſons came to be choſen, and to conſtitute the majority of the Houſe of Commons, who by their Actings have made themſelves infamous and execrable to all Ages, were a Matter too large to penetrate at preſent into the Reaſons of; but that which my Theme conducts me to obſerve, is, That as they ſacrificed the Treaſure of the Nation to the Profuſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Prodigality of the Prince, and our Rights and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to his Ambition and Arbitrary Will, ſo they both intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced and eſtabliſhed thoſe Things which have been a means of dividing us; and by many ſevere and repeated Laws, they ſubjected a great number of induſtrious Engliſh-men and true Proteſtants, to Excommunications, Impriſonments, rigorous and multiplied Fines, and all this for Matters only relating to their Conſciences, and for their Obedience to God in the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of his Worſhip and Houſe. And notwithſtanding the late King's often pretended companion to the Diſſenters, it will be hard to diſcern them, unleſs in Effects which proceed from very different and oppoſite Principles. The diſtance which he kept them from his Perſon and Favour; the influencing theſe Members of both Houſes that depended upon him, to be the Authors and Promoters of Severities againſt them; the enjoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo often the Judges and Juſtices of Peace to execute the Laws upon them in their utmoſt rigour; the inſtigating the Biſhops and Eccleſiaſtical Courts, if at any time they relented in their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions, to purſue them with freſh Citations and Cenſures; the arraigning them, not only upon the Statutes made intentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally againſt Diſſenters, but upon thoſe that were originally and ſolely enacted againſt the Papiſts; theſe, and other Procedures of that Nature, are the only Proofs and Evidences which I can find, of the late King's Bowels, Pity, and Tenderneſs to them. And whereas the weak Church-men were impoſed upon to believe, that all the Severity againſt the Nonconformiſts, was the Fruit of his Zeal for the Proteſtant Religion, and for the ſecurity of the Worſhip und Diſcipline eſtabliſhed by Law; they might have eaſily diſcovered, if Paſſion, Prejudice, Wealth and Honour had not blinded them, that all this was calculated for Ends perfectly deſtructive to the Church, and inconſiſtent with the Safety and Happineſs of all Proteſtants. For as his ſeeking oftner than once to have wriggled himſelf into a Power of ſuperceding and diſpenſing with thoſe Laws and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58012:7"/>ſuſpending their Execution, plainly ſhews that he never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended the ſupport and preſervation of the Church by them; ſo his non-execution of the <hi>Laws</hi> againſt Papiſts; his conniving at their encreaſe; his perſwading thoſe neareſt unto him to reconcile themſelves to the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> as he did, among others, the late Duke of <hi>Monmouth;</hi> his countenancing the Roman Catholicks in their open and intolerable Inſolencies; and his advancing them to the moſt gainful and important Places and Truſts, ſufficiently declare that he never had any love to Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, or care of the Reformed Religion; but that all his Deſigns were of a contrary Tendency, and his faireſt Pretences for the Protection and Grandure of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> adapted to other Ends.</p>
            <p>Thus the Royal Brothers having obtained ſuch <hi>Laws</hi> to be enacted, whereby one Party of Proteſtants was armed with means of oppreſſing and perſecuting all others, neither the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of their Affairs at any time ſince, nor the Application and Interpoſure of ſeveral Parliaments for removing the Grounds of our Differences and Animoſities, by an Indulgence, to be paſt into a <hi>Law,</hi> could prevail, either upon his late Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, or the preſent King, to forgo the Advantage they had gotten of keeping us in mutual Enmity, and thereby of mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring to their projection of ſupplanting our Religion, and re-eſtabliſhing the Faith and Worſhip of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Hereupon the laſt King, not only refuſed to conſent to ſuch Bills as divers late Parliaments had prepared for indulging Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters, and for bringing them into an union of Counſels, and conjunction of Intereſt with thoſe of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> for reſiſting the Conſpiracies of the Papiſts againſt our legal Government and eſtabliſhed Religion; but he rejected an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs for ſuſpending the Execution of the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> againſt Diſſenters, which was offered and preſented unto him by that very Parliament which had framed and enacted thoſe cruel and hard <hi>Laws.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as the Royal Brothers have made it their conſtant Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to cheriſh a Diviſion and Rancour among Proteſtants, and to provoke one Party to perſecute and ruin another; ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could more naturally fall in with the Deſign of Arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſs, or be more ſubſervient to the betraying the Nation to Papal Idolatry and Juriſdiction. For ſeveral <hi>Penal Laws.</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:58012:8"/>againſt a conſiderable Body of People, do either expoſe them againſt whom they are enacted, to be deſtroyed by the Prince, with whom the executive Power of the <hi>Law</hi> is truſted and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſited; or they prove a Temptation to ſuch as are obnoxious of reſigning themſelves in ſuch a manner to the Will and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Monarch, for the obtaining his connivancy at their violation of the <hi>Laws,</hi> as is unſafe and dangerous for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Liberty and Good of the Kingdom. For in caſe the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Magiſtrate purſue an Intereſt diſtinct from, and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to that of his People, they who the <hi>Law</hi> hath made liable to be oppreſſed, are brought under Inducements of becoming ſo many Partiſans for abetting him in his Deſigns, in hopes of being thereupon protected from the Penal Statutes, the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whereof is committed to him. And as it is not agreeable to the Wiſdom and Prudence which ought to be among Men, nor to the Mercy and Compaſſion which ſhould be among Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, for one Party to ſurrender another into the Hands and Power of the Sovereign, to be impoveriſhed and ruined by him at his pleaſure, eſpecially when thoſe whom they give up to be thus treated and entertained, are at agreement with them in all the Eſſentials of Religion, equally zealous as themſelves for the Liberties of their Country; and who, for Sobriety in their Lives, Induſtry in their Callings, and Uſefulneſs in the Common-Wealth, are inferior to none of their Fellow-Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects: So it is obvious to any who give themſelves leave to think, that the King would long ere this have been ſtated in the Abſoluteneſs that is aſpired after, and both Church and State reduced to lie at the diſcretion of the Monarch, provided the Nonconformiſts, for procuring his Favour in non-execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Laws, had ſuffered themſelves to be prevailed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and drawn over to ſtand by and aſſiſt him in his Popiſh and Deſpotical Deſigns.</p>
            <p>But that honeſt People, though hated and maligned by their Brethren, rather than be found aiding the King in his Uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions over the Kingdom, have choſen to undergo the utmoſt Calamities they could be made ſubject unto, either through the Execution of thoſe Laws which had been made againſt them, or through our Princes and their Miniſters wrecking their Malice upon them in Arbitrary and Illegal Methods. But what the Royal Brothers could not work the afflicted and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:58012:8"/>Side unto, they found the Art to engage the other Side in, tho not only excepted from all Obnoxiouſneſs to thoſe Laws, but ſtrengthened and ſupported by them. For as ſoon as the Court begun to deſpair of prevailing upon Diſſenters to become <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir Tools and Inſtruments of enſlaving the Nation, and of exalting the Monarchy to a deſpotical Abſoluteneſs, they applied to the Bigots of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> whom by gratifying with a vigorous Execution of the Laws upon Diſſenters, they brought to abet, applaud, and juſtify them in all thoſe Counſels and Ways which have reduced us into that miſerable condition wherein we not long ſince were. The Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy being advanced to Grandure and Opulency, things which many of them are fonder of, and loather to forgo than Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and the Rights of the Nation, the Court made it their buſineſs to poſſeſs them with a Belief, that unleſs the Fanaticks were ſuppreſſed and ruined, they could not enjoy with Security their Dignities and Wealth. Whereupon not only the leſſer Levites, but the Superior Clergy having their Leſſon and Cue given them from <hi>White-hall</hi> and St. <hi>James</hi>'s, fell upon purſuing the Nonconformiſts with Eccleſiaſtical Puniſhments, and upon exciting and animating the Civil Officers againſt them. And under pretence of preſerving and defending the Church, they gave themſelves over to an implicit ſerving of the Court, and became not only Advocates but Inſtruments for the robbing of Corporations of their Charters, for impoſing Sheriffs upon the City of <hi>London</hi> who had not been legally elected, and of fining and puniſhing Men arbitrarily for no Crime, ſave the having aſſerted their own and the Nations Rights in modeſt and lawful ways. Poſterity will hardly believe that ſo many of the Prelatical Clergy, and ſo great a number of Members of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſhould from an Enmity unto, and pretended Jealouſie of the Diſſenters, have become Tools un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the late King for juſtifying the Diſſolution of ſo many Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, the Invaſion made upon their Priviledges, the ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and ſtifling of the Popiſh Plot, the ſhamming of forged Conſpiracies upon Proteſtants, the condemning ſeveral to Death for High-Treaſon, who could be rendred guilty by the Trangreſſion of no known Law, and finally for advancing a Gentleman to the Throne, who had been engaged in a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juration againſt Religion and the Legal Government, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:58012:9"/>whom three ſeveral Parliaments would have therefore excluded from the Right of Succeſſion. And being ſeduced into an eſpouſal of the Intereſts of the Court againſt Religion, Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and the Nation, it is doleful to conſider what Doctrines both from Pulpit and Preſs were thereupon brought forth and divulged. Such as Monarchy's being a Government by Divine Right; that it is in the Prince's Power to rule as he pleaſeth; that it is a Grace and Condeſcention in the King to give an account of what he does; that for Parliaments to direct, or regulate the Succeſſion, borders upon Treaſon, and is an Offence againſt the Law of Nature; and that the only thing left to Subjects, in caſe the King will tyrannize over their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, Perſons, and Eſtates, is tamely to ſuffer, and as ſome of them did abſurdly expreſs it, to exerciſe Paſſive Obedience. So that by corrupting the Minds and Conſciences of Men with thoſe peſtilent and ſlaviſh Notions, they betrayed the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion both to the Miſchiefs which have already overtaken us, and to what further we were threatned with. Nor did theſe Doctrines tend meerly to the fettering and enfeebling the Spirits of Men, but they were a Temptation to the Royal Brothers to put in Execution what they had been ſo long contriving and travelling with, and were a kind of repri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding them for being ignorant of their own Right and Power, and for not exerting it with that Vigor and Expedition which they might. I do acknowledg that there were many both of the Sacred Order, and of the Laick Communion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who were far from being infected with thoſe brutiſh Sentiments and Opinions, and who were as zealous as any for having the Monarchy kept within its ancient limits; Parliaments maintained in their wonted Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and Authority; the Subjects preſerved in the enjoyment of their immemorial Priviledges; and who were far from ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificing our Religion and Laws to Popery and Arbitrarineſs; and from lulling us into a Tameneſs and Lethargy, in caſe the Court ſhould attempt the aboliſhing the eſtabliſhed Doctrine and Worſhip, and the ſubverting and changing the Civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. But alas! beſides their being immediately branded with the Name of <hi>Trimmer</hi> and conformable <hi>Fanaticks,</hi> and regiſtred in the Kalender with thoſe that ſtood precluded the King's Favour, and merited his Animadverſion; their
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:58012:9"/>Modeſty was ſoon drowned and ſilenced in the loud Noiſe of their clamorous Brethren, and their retiredneſs from Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, while the others frequented all places of Society and publick Concourſe, deprived the Nation of the benefit of their Example, and the happineſs of their Inſtructions. Nor have I mentioned the Extravagancies of any of the Eccleſiaſticks and Members of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> with a deſign either of reproaching and upbraiding them, or of provoking and exaſperating the Diſſenters to Reſentments, but only to ſhew how fatal our Diviſions have been unto us, what Exceſſes they have occaſioned our being hurried and tranſported into, and what miſchievous Improvement our Enemies have made of them, to the ſupplanting and almoſt ſubverting of all that is valuable unto us, as we are Engliſh-men, Chriſtians, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants.</p>
            <p>And as our Animoſities, through our Diviſions, gave the Court an advantage of ſuborning that Party, which they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to befriend and uphold, into a Miniſtration to all their Counſels, and Projections againſt our Religion and Laws; ſo by reaſon of the unnatural Heats wherewith Proteſtants have been enflamed and enraged againſt Proteſtants, many weak, ungrounded, and unſtable Souls, have been tempted to queſtion the Truth of our Religion, and to apoſtatize to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and thereupon have become united in Inclination, Power, and endeavours with the Court, and our old Enemies the Papiſts, for the extirpation of Proteſtancy, and the altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Government. As it hath been matter of Offence and Scandal to all Men, ſo it hath been ground of ſtumbling and falling unto many, to ſee thoſe who are profeſſedly of the ſame Religion, to be mutually embittered againſt one another, and ſo far tranſported with Malice and Rage, as to ſeek and purſue each others Deſtruction. For ſuch a Carriage and Behaviour are ſo contrary to the Spirit and Principles of Chriſtianity, and to the Genius and Temper of true Religion, that it is no marvel if Perſons ignorant of the Holy Scriptures, and ſtrangers to the converting and comforting Vertue of the Doctrine of the Goſpel aſſerted in our Confeſſions, and inſiſted upon by our Divines, ſhould ſuſpect the Orthodoxy of that Religion which is accompanied with ſo bitter Fruits, even in the Diſpenſers of the Word as well as in others, and betake
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:58012:10"/>themſelves to the Communion of that Church, where how many and important ſoever their Differences be one with another, yet they do not break ſorth into thoſe Flames of excommunicating and perſecuting each other, that ours have done. How have ſome among us, through having their Spirits fretted and exaſperated by the craft and cunning of our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, not only loaded and ſtigmatized their Brethren and fellow-Proteſtants with Crimes and Names, which were they true and deſerved, would juſtly render us a loathing and an Abomination to Mankind, but have libelled and branded thoſe whom God had honoured to be Inſtruments of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, with Appellations and Characters fit to beget a deteſtation of their Doctrine as well as their Memory. The worſt that the Papiſts have forged and vomited out againſt <hi>Luther, Zwinglius, Calvin,</hi> &amp;c. hath been raked up and repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the diſparagement of the Reformation, and to the ſcandalizing the Minds of weak Men againſt it. And as the Jeſuits and Prieſts have improved thoſe Slanders and Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies to the Seduction of divers from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and to a working them over to a Reconciliation with the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> ſo the Court hath thereby had an increaſe of their Faction and Party againſt our Religion and Liberties, and have been inabled to muſter Troops of <hi>Janiſaries</hi> for their Deſpotical and Unlimited Claim.</p>
            <p>Nor have our Diviſions, with the Heats, Animoſities, Revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and Perſecutions that have enſued thereupon, proved only an occaſion of the Seduction of ſeveral from our Religion, and of their Apoſtacy to Popery, but they have been a main ſpring and ſource of the Debauchery, Irreligion, and Atheiſm, which have overſpread the Nation, and have brought ſo many both to an indifferency and unconcernedneſs for the Goſpel, and all that is vertuous and noble, and have diſpoſed them to fall in with thoſe that could countenance and protect them in their Impiety and Prophaneneſs, and feed their Luxury and Pride with Honour and Gain. What a woful Scheme of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion have we afforded the World! and how ſhamefully have we painted forth and repreſented the holy Doctrine of the bleſſed Jeſus, while we have not only lived in a direct oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to all the Commands of Meekneſs, Love, and mutual forbearance which our Religion lays us under the Authority of,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:58012:10"/>but have neglected to practiſe good manners, to obſerve the Rules of Civility, to treat one another with common Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and to do as we would be done unto? While we have been more offended at what ſeemed to ſupplant our Domina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Grandures, than at what diſhonoured God and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached the Goſpel; while we weighed not ſo much whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they whom we took into our ſacred Communion, as well as into our perſonal Friendſhip, were conformable in their Lives to the Scripture, as whether they complied with the Canons of the Church, while we reprobated all that were not of our way, though never ſo vertuous and devout, and ſainted all that were, though never ſo wicked and prophane; while we branded ſuch for Fanaticks, whom we could juſtly charge with nothing, ſave the not admitting that into Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which came not from the Divine Author of it; and hugged thoſe for good and Orthodox Believers, that would ſooner conſult the Statute-Book for their Practice in the Worſhip of God, than the Bible; while we haled thoſe to Priſon and ſpoiled them of their Eſtates, to whom nothing could be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, except their being too preciſe and conſciencious, in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voiding that, through fear and apprehenſion of ſinning, which others had a liberty and latitude to do, as judging it lawful, and in the mean time eſteemed thoſe worthy of the chiefeſt Truſts in the Church and Common-wealth, whoſe Folly and Villanies made them unfit for Civil Societies; while they who lived moſt agreeably to the Laws of God and the Example of Chriſt, were perſecuted as Enemies to Religion and the Peſts of the Kingdom, and in the interim too many of the very Clergy were not only Countenances of the moſt profligate Perſons as their beſt Friends, but joined and aſſiſted in ſcandalous De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baucheries, under pretence of ſuſtaining the Honour of their Tribe, and doing Service to the Church. I ſay, while theſe were the unhappy, but too obvious Fruits of our Diviſions, and of the bitter Heats that accompanied them, how was the Reverence for the Sacred Order leſſened and diminiſhed, the Veneration for Religion weakned and loſt, the Shame and Dread of appearing prophane and wicked, removed and ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed; and ſuch who took the meaſures of Chriſtianity from the Practices of thoſe that were ſtiled Chriſtians, rather than
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:58012:11"/>from the immaculate and holy Scriptures, tempted to think all Religion a Juggle, and Prieſthood but an Artifice and Craft to compaſs Honour and Wealth. And though nothing but a ſhortneſs of Underſtanding, and an immoderate Love to their Luſts, could occaſion the drawing ſuch a Concluſion from the foregoing Premiſes, yet I muſt needs grant that there was too juſt a ground adminiſtred unto them of ſaying, that many did not believe that themſelves, the Faith whereof they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended to others. But that which I would more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly obſerve is, that it is from among thoſe, who by the foregoing occaſions have been tempted to Debauchery and Irreligion, that the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Emiſaries have made the Harveſt of Proſelytes and Converts to the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> For as they who fear not God will, be eaſily brought to imitate <hi>Ceaſar;</hi> and ſuch who are of no Religion will, in ſubſerviency to Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Ends, aſſume the Mask and Profeſſion of any: ſo Popery is extreamly adapted to the Wiſhes and Deſires of wicked and profane Men, in that it provides for their living as enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly as they pleaſe here, and flatters them with hopes and aſſurances of Bleſſedneſs hereafter. They who can be aſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained of going to Heaven upon their confeſſing their Sins to a Prieſt, and their receiving Abſolution, the Euchariſt and Extream Unction, need not look after Repentance towards God, Converſion to Holineſs, nor a Life of Faith, Love, Mortification and Obedience, which the Proteſtant Religion, upon the Authority of the Goſpel, obligeth them unto, in order to the obtaining of Eternal Happineſs. And as the late Apoſtates to Popery in <hi>England,</hi> are chiefly ſuch who were notorious for Looſeneſs, Prophaneneſs and Immorality, and were the Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal of our Religion while they profeſſed it; and while in our Church, were not properly of it: ſo it is from among Men of this ſtamp and character, that their late Majeſties have found Perſons aſſiſting and ſubſervient to their Deſpotical and Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Deſigns. For whoſoever takes a Survey of the Court-Faction, and conſidereth who have been the Advocates for Enchroachments upon our Liberties, and Abetters of Uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions over our Rights, they will find them to have been prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally the profligate and debauched among the Nobility and Gentry, the mercinary, ignorant and ſcandalous among the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:58012:11"/>Clergy, the Off-ſcouring and ſuch as are an Ignominy to Human Nature among the Yeomanry and Peaſants. And it was in order to this villanous End, that the Royal Brothers have endeavoured ſo induſtriouſly to debauch the Nation, and have made Senſuality and Profaneneſs the Qualifications for Preferment, and the Badges of Loyalty. And if among thoſe that appear for the Preſervation of the Liberties of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, there be any that deſerve to be ſtiled Enemies to Religion and Vertue, as I dare affirm that they owe their Immoralities to Court-Education, Converſe and Example; ſo I hope that though they have not hitherto been all of them ſo happy as to have left their Vices where they learned them, yet that they will not continue to diſparage the good Cauſe which they have eſpouſed with an unſutable Life, nor give their Adverſarie; reaſon to ſay, that while they pretend to ſeek the Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the State, they are both the Deriders of Sobriety and Vertue, without which no Conſtitution can long ſubſiſt, and guilty of ſuch horrid Oaths, Curſing, Imprecations, Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and Uncleanneſſes, which naturally, as well as morally and meritoriouſly, diſpoſe Nations to Subverſion and Extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation.</p>
            <p>Finally, Being through the bitter Effects which have enſued upon our Diviſions, made apprehenſive and jealous one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, it hath from thence come to paſs, that while the Care of the Conformiſts hath been to watch againſt the growth of the Diſſenters; and the ſollicitude of the Nonconformiſts hath been, how to prevent the Rage of the biggotted Church-men, the Papiſts, in the mean time, without being heeded or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, have both incredibly multiplied, and made conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Advances in their deſigns of ruining us. For whenſoever the Court was to take a ſignal ſtep towards Popery and Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Power, there was a clamour raiſed of ſome menacing Boldneſs of the Diſſenters. And if the Nation grew at any time allarmed, by reaſon of the Favour ſhewn to the Roman Catholicks, and of ſome viſible Progreſs made towards the King's becoming Deſpotical, all was immediately huſh'd with a ſhout and cry of the Government and Church's being in immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent hazard from the Diſſenters. Yea, whenſoever the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts and their Royal Patrons ſtood detected, of having been
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:58012:12"/>conſpiring againſt our Religion and Civil Liberties, all was di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erted and ſtiſled, by putting the Kingdom upon a falſe Scent, and by hounding out their Beagles upon the Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts. So that the Eyes and Minds of Proteſtants being imployed in reference to what was to be apprehended and feared from one another, the working of our Popiſh Enemies either eſcaped our Obſervation, or were heeded by moſt, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with a ſuperficial and unaffective Glance. And while our Church-men ſtood prepoſſeſſed by the Court, with a dread and jealouſy of the Diſſenters, all that was ſaid and written of a Conſpiracy carried on by the Papiſts againſt our <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> was entertained and repreſented by the prejudiced Clergy, as an Artifice only of the Diſſenters for compaſſing an Indulgence from the Parliament, which in caſe ſuch a Plot had obtained the belief, that a Matter of ſo great Danger and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence required, would have been eaſily granted, being the only rational Expedient for the preſervation of the eſtabliſhed Religion and the legal Government. Nor did our Enemies queſtion, but that having enflamed our Diviſions, and raiſed our Animoſities to ſo great a height, rather than the one Party would lay aſide their Severities, and the other let fall their Reſentments, we would even be contented to lie at their Mercy, and ſubmit our ſelves to the Pleaſure and Diſcretion of the Court and Papiſts. And there have not wanted ſome peeviſh, fooliſh, and ill Men of both Parties, who rather than ſacrifice their Spleen and Paſſion, and abandon their particular Quarrels for the Intereſt and Safety of the whole, have been inclined to expoſe the Proteſtant Religion and Engliſh Liberties, to the Hazards wherewith they were apparently threatned, and to ſuffer all Extremities, meerly to have the ſatisfaction of ſeeing thoſe whom they reſpectively hate, involved with them under the ſame Miſeries. But as this was ſuch a degree of Madneſs and Infatuation, as could proceed from nothing but brutiſh Rage, and argues no leſs than a Divine <hi>Nemeſis;</hi> ſo, I hope, they are but few that now ſtand infected with theſe paſſionate Sentiments and Inclinations, and remain thus hardned in their mutual Prejudices. And to thoſe I have nothing to ſay, nor the leaſt Advice to adminiſter, but ſhall leave them to their own Follies, as Perſons to whoſe Conviction no Diſcourſe,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:58012:12"/>though never ſo rational, can be adapted, and whom only Stripes can work upon.</p>
            <p>'Tis to ſuch therefore as are capable of hearkning to Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and who are ready to embrace any Counſel that ſhall be found adjuſted to the Common Intereſt, that I am to addreſs what remains to be repreſented and ſaid in the following Leaves. For all Parties of Proteſtants having ſeen how far our Enemies have improved our Diviſions and Rancours, to the compaſſing their wicked and ambitious Deſigns, and the rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing us of all that good and generous Men account valuable; they are at laſt convinced of the neceſſity we have been and are reduced unto, of altering the meaſures of our acting towards one another, and both of laying aſide our Perſecutions, and of exchanging our Wranglings among our ſelves, into a joint contending for the Faith of the Goſpel, and the Rights of the Nation. For what the Gentleman, ſo lately in the Throne, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends and aims at, is not any longer matter of meer Suſpicion and Jealouſy, but of demonſtrable Evidence and unqueſtiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Certainty.</p>
            <p>His Mask and Vizor of Zeal for the preſervation of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and of tender regard for the Laws of the Land, were laid by and put off, and his Reſolutions of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning Arbitrarily, and of introducing Popery, were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come obvious to all Men, whom Reaſon and Senſe have not forſaken and left.</p>
            <p>The Papiſts, whom it was thought much, a while ago, to ſee connived at in the exerciſe of their Worſhip in private Houſes, are allowed now to practiſe their Idolatry openly in our chief Towns, and in the Metropolitan City of the Kingdom to uſurp the publick Churches and Cathedrals. Thoſe Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Gentlemen, whom heretofore it was matter of ſurpriſe to ſee countenanced with the private Favour of the Prince, are now advanced to the ſupream Commands in the Army, and the principal Truſt in Civil Affairs. The Recuſant Lords, whoſe enlargement out of the <hi>Tower,</hi> we could not but look upon as an unpreſidented Violation, both of the Laws of the Land, and of the Rights and Juriſdiction of Parliament, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing committed thither by the Authority of the Houſe of Lords, upon a Charge and Impeachment of High Treaſon, by the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:58012:13"/>Commons of <hi>England</hi> in Parliament aſſembled, were now ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured to be Members of the Privy Council, and exalted to be chief Miniſters of State. They whom the Statutes of the Realm make ſubject to the ſevereſt Penalties for Apoſtacy to <hi>Rome,</hi> are not only protected from the edg of the Laws, but maintained in Parochial Incumbencies, and Headſhips of Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges.</p>
            <p>Our Orthodox Clergy are not only inhibited to preach a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Popery, but are illegally Reprimanded, Silenced, and Suſpended, for diſcharging that Duty which their Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Offices, Oaths, and the Laws of the Kingdom oblige them unto. And ſuch whom neither the Eccleſiaſtical nor <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> Courts can arraign and proceed againſt, we had a new Court of Inquiſition erected for the adjudging and puniſhing of them. So that it is not the Diſſenters who are the only Perſons to be ſtruck at and ruined, but the Conformiſts are to be treated after the ſame manner, and to ſhare in the common Lot whereunto all honeſt and ſincere Proteſtants are deſtined and deſigned. Even they who were the Darlings of <hi>Whitehall</hi> and St. <hi>Jameſes,</hi> and recompenſed with Honours and Titles for betraying the Rights and Priviledges of Corporations, perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting Diſſenters, and heading Addreſſes, wherein Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were reproached, the Courſe of Juſtice againſt Popiſh Offenders was ſlandered, the illegal and arbitrary procedures of the Court applauded and juſtified, and all that were zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for our Laws and Liberties ſtigmatized with the Names of <hi>Villains</hi> and <hi>Traitors,</hi> are now themſelves, for but diſcouraging Popiſh Aſſemblies, and attempting to put the Laws in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt Prieſts who had publickly celebrated Maſs, not only check'd and rebuked, but puniſhed with Seiſure and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment.</p>
            <p>Nor are our Religion and Civil Liberties meerly ſupplanted and undermined by illegal Tricks, gloſſed over with the Var<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh of judicial Forms, but they are aſſaulted and battered in the face of the Sun, without ſo much as a palliation to give their procedures a plauſible figure. And the King being brought to a deſpair of managing the Parliament to his barefaced Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes of Popery and Arbitrarineſs, and of prevailing with them to eſtabliſh Tyranny and Idolatry by Law, notwithſtanding
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:58012:13"/>their having been as induſtriouſly pack'd and choſen to anſwer ſuch a Deſign, as Art, Bribery and Authority could reach; and notwithſtanding their having been obſequious in their firſt Seſſion to an exceſs that has proved unſafe to themſelves &amp; the Nation, he became reſolved not to allow them to meet any more, but to ſet up <hi>a-la-mode de France,</hi> and to have his perſonal Commands, ſeconded with the Aſſent of his <hi>durarte-beneplacito</hi> Judges, to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged and obeyed for Laws. So that they who were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ſeduced into a good Opinion of him, are not only unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, but provoked to warm Reſentments, for having had their credulity and eaſineſs of belief ſo groſly abuſed. And as the converting ſo a vaſt a number of well-meaning, but wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully deluded People, who had ſuffered themſelves to de hood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wink'd, and fatally hurried to betray their Religion, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and Poſterity, to the Ambition and Popiſh Bigottry of the Court, was a deſign becoming the Compaſſion, Mercy and Wiſdom of God; ſo the Method's and Means whereby they are come to be enlightned and proſelyted, are a ſignal vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sapience and Righteouſneſs of God in all thoſe tremendous ſteps of his Providence, by which our Enemies have been emboldned to detect and diſcover themſelves. For though their continuing ſo long to have a good opinion of the preſent King, and their abetting him ſo far in the undermining our Religion, and invading our Liberties, may ſeem to have proceeded not ſo much from their Ignorance, as from their Obſtinacy and Malice; yet God, who penetrates into the Hearts of Men, may have diſcovered ſome degrees of ſincerity in their Pretentious and Carriages, though accompanied with a great deal of folly and unmanlineſs. Nor are the Lord's ways like to ours, to give Perſons over as unteachable and irreclaimable, upon their withſtanding every meaſure of Light, and the reſiſting even thoſe Means which were ſufficient and proper for their Conviction; but he will try them by now and extraordinary Methods, and ſee whether Feeling and dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Experience may not convert thoſe, upon whom Arguments and moral Evidence could make no impreſſions. And there being among thoſe formerly miſled and deluded Proteſtants, many who retained a Love for their Country, a Care for their Poſterity, and a Zeal for the Goſpel and Reformed Religion,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:58012:14"/>even when their Actions imported the contrary, and ſeem'd to betray them; the ſingling and weeding out ſuch from among the Court-Faction and Party, is a compenſation both for the defeatment of all endeavours, for the prevention of the Evils that have overtaken us, and for the Diſtreſſes and Calamities under which we do at preſent lie and groan. And if there be joy in Heaven upon the converſion of a Sinner, with what thankfulneſs to God, and joy in themſelves, ſhould they who have ſo many Years wreſtled againſt the encroachments of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery and Arbitrarineſs, and who have deeply ſuffered in their Names, Perſons and Eſtates upon that account, welcome and embrace their once erring and miſled, but now enlightned, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed and converted Brethren? And inſtead of remembring or upbraiding them with the oppoſition and rancour which they expreſſed againſt our Perſons, Principles, and Ways, let there be no Language heard from us, but what may declare the joy we have in our ſelves for their converſion, and the entire truſt and confidence which we put in them.</p>
            <p>The firſt Duty incumbent therefore upon Diſſenters towards thoſe of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> is to believe, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding there have been many of them ſo long Advocates and Partiſans for the Court, through ignorance of what was aimed at and intended, they are nevertheleſs as really concerned as any others, and as truly zealous for the preſervation of the Proteſtant Religion, and for maintaining the legal Rights and Liberties of the Subject, and when occaſion ſhall offer, will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove themſelves accordingly. 'Tis a ridiculous, as well as a miſchievous Fancy, for one Party to confine all Religion only to themſelves, or to circumſcribe all the ancient Engliſh Ardor for the common Rights of the Nation, to ſuch as are of their particular Fellowſhip and Perſwaſion, there being ſincere Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and true Engliſhmen among thoſe of all Judgments and Societies of Proteſtants, and among none more than thoſe of the Communion of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> It were the height of Wickedneſs, as well as the moſt prodigious Folly, to imagine that the <hi>Conformiſts</hi> have abandoned all Fidelity to God, and caſt off all Care of themſelves and their Country, upon a miſtaken Judgment of being Loyal and Obedient to the King. The contrary is plain enough; they knew as well as any, that
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:58012:14"/>the giving to <hi>Ceſar</hi> the Things that are <hi>Ceſar</hi>'s, lay them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der no Obligation of ſurrendring unto him the Things that are God's; nor of ſacrificing unto the Will of the Sovereign the Priviledges reſerved unto the People by the Fundamental Rules of the Conſtitution, and by the Statutes of the Realm. And they underſtand, as well as others, that the Laws of the Land are the only Meaſures of the Prince's Authority, and of the Subjects Fealty; and where they give him no Right to Command, they lay them under no tie to Obey. And though here and there a Diſſenter has written againſt Popery with good Succeſs, yet they have been moſtly Conformable Divines, who have triumphed over it in elaborate Diſcourſes, and who have beaten the Romiſh Scriblers off the Stage. Nor can it be thought that they who have ſo accurately related and vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated the Hiſtory, and aſſerted and defended the Doctrine of the Reformation, ſhould either tamely relinquiſh, or be wanting in all due and legal Ways to uphold and maintain it. And though ſome few of the Nonconformiſts have, with ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient ſtrength and applauſe, uſed their Pens againſt Arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſs, in detecting the Deſigns of the Royal Brothers, yet they who have generally, and with greateſt Honour, appeared for our Laws and Legal Government, againſt the Invaſions and Uſurpations of the Court, have been Theologues and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Nor in caſe of further At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts for altering the Conſtitution, and enſlaving the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, will they ſhew themſelves unworthy the having deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from Anceſtors, whoſe Motto in the high Places of the Field was, <hi>nolumus Leges Angliae mutari.</hi> They who have ſo often juſtified the Arms of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Netherlands</hi> againſt their Rightful Princes the Kings of <hi>Spain,</hi> and ſo unanſwerably vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated their caſting off Obedience to thoſe Monarchs, when they had invaded their Privileges, and attempted to eſtabliſh the <hi>Inquiſition</hi> over them, cannot be ignorant what their own Right and Duty is in behalf of the Proteſtant Religion and Engliſh Liberties; for the Security whereof, we have not only ſo many Laws, but the Coronation Oaths, and Stipulations of our Kings.</p>
            <p>And thoſe Gentlemen of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared ſo vigorouſly in three Parliaments for excluding the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:58012:15"/>Duke of <hi>York,</hi> from the Succeſſion to the Crown, by reaſon of a Jealouſy of what, through being a Papiſt, he would at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt againſt our Religion and Priviledges, in caſe he were ſuffered to aſcend the Throne; cannot be now to ſeek what becomes them towards him, having ſeen and felt what before they only apprehended and feared. For if the Law that entail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Succeſſion upon the next of Kin, and obligeth the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to admit and receive him, not only may, but ought to be diſpenſed with, in caſe the Heir, thrô having imbib'd Principles which threaten the Safety, and are inconſiſtent with the Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of the People, hath made himſelf incapable to inherit; we know, by a ſhort Ratiocination, how far we ſtand bound to a Prince on the Throne, who by tranſgreſſing againſt the Laws of the Conſtitution, hath abdicated himſelf from the Government, and ſtands virtually Depoſed. For whoſoever ſhall offer to rule Arbitrarily, does immediately ceaſe to be King <hi>de jure,</hi> ſeeing by the Fundamental, Common, and Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute Laws of the Realm, we know none for Supream Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate and Governor, but a limited Prince, and one who ſtands circumſcribed and bounded in his Power and Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</p>
            <p>And ſhould the Diſſenters entertain a belief that the Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts are leſs concerned and zealous than themſelves for the Proteſtant Religion, and Laws of the Kingdom, they would not only ſin, and offend againſt the Rules of Charity, but againſt the Meaſures of Juſtice, and daily Evidences from Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Fact. For neither they, nor we, owe out Converſion to God, and our practical Holineſs to the Opinions about Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, Forms of Worſhip, and Ceremonies, wherein we differ, but the Doctrines of Faith and Chriſtian Obedience, wherein we agree. 'Tis not their being for a Liturgy, a Surpliſs, or a Biſhop, that hath heretofore influenced them to ſubſerve the Court in Deſigns tending to Abſoluteneſs, but they were ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced unto it, upon Motives whereof they are now aſhamed; and the ridiculouſneſs and folly of which they have at laſt diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd. Nor is the multitude of profligate and ſcandalous Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, with which the Church of <hi>England</hi> is crowded, any juſt impeachment of the Purity of her Doctrine in the Vitals and Eſſentials of Religion, or of the Vertue and Piety of many of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:58012:15"/>her Members. For as it is her being the only Society eſtabliſhed by Law that attracts thoſe Vermin to her Boſom, ſo it Is her being reſtrained by Law from debarring them, that keeps them there to her reproach, and to the grief of many of her Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticks. Neither is it the fault of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that the Agents and Factors for Popery and Arbitrary Power, have choſen to paſs under the Name of <hi>her Sons;</hi> but it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds partly from their Malice, as hoping by that means to diſgrace her with all true Engliſh-men, as well as with Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; and partly from their Craft, in order thereby the better to conceal their Deſign, and to ſhrowd themſelves from the Cenſure and Puniſhment; which had it not been for that Mask, they would have been expoſed unto, and have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone. And I dare affirm, that beſides the Obligations from Religon, which the Conformiſts are equally under with Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, for hindring the introduction of Popery, there are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Inducements from intereſt which ſway them to prevent its eſtabliſhment, wherein the Diſſenters are but little concerned. For though Popery would he alike afflictive to the Conſciences of Proteſtants of all Perſuaſions, yet they are Gentlemen, and Miniſters of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> whole Livings, Revenues, and Eſtates have been threatned in caſe it had come to be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed.</p>
            <p>Nor would the moſt Loyal and obſequious Levites, provided they reſolve to continue Proteſtants, be willing that their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonages and Incumbencies, to which they have no leſs Right by Law, than the King hath to the Exciſe and Cuſtoms, ſhould be taken from them and beſtowed upon Romiſh Prieſts, by an Act of Deſpotical Power, and of unlimited Prerogative. And for the Gentlemen, as I think few of them would hold themſelves obliged to part with their Purſes to High-way Padders, though ſuch ſhould have a Patent from the King to rob whomſoever they met upon the Road; ſo there will not be many inclined to ſuffer their Manours and Abbey-Lands, to which they have ſo good a Title, to be raviſhed from them either by Monks or Janizaries, though authoriſed thereunto by the Prince's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion. Even they who had formerly, ſuffered themſelves to be ſeduced, to prove, in a manner, Betrayers of the Rights and Religion of their Country, will now (being undeceived) not
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:58012:16"/>only in conjunction with others, withſtand the Court in its proſecution of Popiſh and Arbitrary Deſigns; but through a generous exaſperation, for having been deluded and abuſed, will judg themſelves obliged, in vindication of their Actings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to appear for the Proteſtant Religion, and the Laws of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> with a Zeal equal to that wherewith they contributed to the undermining and ſupplanting of them. For they are not only become more ſenſible than they were of the Miſchiefs of Abſolute Government, ſo as for the ſuture to prize and aſſert the Priviledges reſerved unto the People by the Rules of the Conſtitution, and chalk'd out for them in the Laws of the Land; but they have ſuch a freſh view of Popery, both in its Hereſies, Blaſphemies, Superſtitions, and Idolatries; and in the Treachery, Sanguinarineſs, Violence and Cruelty which the Papal Principles mould, influence, and oblige Men unto; that they not only entertain the greateſt abhorrency and dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation imaginable for it, but ſeem reſolved not to cheriſh in their Boſom, a Thing ſo abominable to God, execrable to good Men, and deſtructive to Humane as well as to Chriſtian Societies.</p>
            <p>Nor are the Diſſenters meerly to believe that the Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts are equally zealous as themſelves for the Reformed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and Engliſh Rights, but they are to conſider them as the only great and united Body of Proteſtants in the Kingdom, with whom all other Parties compared bear no conſiderable proportion. For though the Nonconformiſts, conſidered ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractly, make a vaſt number of honeſt and uſeful People, yet being laid in the Scale with thoſe of the Epiſcopal Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they are but few, and lie in a little room. And whoſoever will take the pains to ballance the one againſt the other, even where Diſſenters make the greateſt Figure, and may juſtly boaſt of their Multitude, they will ſoon be convinced that the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the other doth far tranſcend and exceed them. And if it be ſo in Cities and Corporations, where the greateſt Bulk of Diſſenters are, it is much more ſo in Country Pariſhes, where the latter bear not the proportion of one to a hundred. Nor doth the Church of <hi>England</hi> more exceed the other Parties in her number, than ſhe doth in the quality of her Members. For whereas they who make up and conſtitute the ſeparate Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:58012:16"/>are chiefly Perſons of the middle Rank and Condition; the Church of <hi>England</hi> doth in a manner vouch, and claim all the Perſons of Honour, of the Learned Profeſſions, and ſuch as have valuable Eſtates, for her Communicants. And though the other ſort are as neceſſary in the Common-Wealth, and contribute as much to its Strength, Proſperity, and Happineſs, yet they make not that Figure in the Government, nor ſtand in that Capacity of having influence upon Publick Affairs. For not only the Gentlemen of both the Gowns, who by reaſon of their Calling and Learning are beſt able to defend our Religion, and vindicate our Laws and Priviledges with their Tongues and Pens, but they whoſe Eſtates, Reputation, and Intereſt, recommendeth them to be elected Members of the great Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate of the Nation, as well as they, who by reaſon of their Honours and Baronages, are Hereditary Legiſlators, are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, if not all, of the Communion of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> So that they who conform to the eſtabliſhed Worſhip and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, are to be look'd upon and acknowledged as the great Bulwark of the Proteſtant Religion in <hi>England,</hi> and the Hedg and Fence of our Civil Liberties and Rights.</p>
            <p>And though it be true, that this great Breach made upon our Religion and Laws is fallen out under their hand, while the poor Diſſenters had neither acceſſion to, nor were in a condition to prevent; it yet ſeeing their own Conſciences do ſufficiently load and charge them for it with Shame and Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominy, it were neither candid, nor at this Juncture ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to upbraid it to them, or improve it to their Diſhonour and Reproach. For as they have tamely look'd on and connived till our Religion and Liberties are ſo far under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined and ſupplanted; ſo it is they alone who have been in a condition of ſtemming the Inundation of Idolatry and Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, with which we were threatned, and of repairing our Breaches, and reducing the Prerogative to its old Channel, and making Popery ſneak and retreat into its holes and corners again. And ſhould the Church of <hi>England</hi> have been overthrown and devoured, what an eaſie Prey would the reſt have been to the Romiſh Cormorants! And could the King, under the Conduct of the Jeſuits, and with the aſſiſtance of his <hi>Myrmidons,</hi> have diſſolved the eſtabliſhed Worſhip and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:58012:17"/>they of the Separation would have been in no capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city to ſupport the Reformed Religion, nor able to eſcape the common Ruine and Perſecution. 'Tis therefore the Intereſt, as well as the Duty of the Diſſenters, to help maintain and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend thoſe Walls, within the skreen and ſhelter whereof their own Huts and Cottages are built and ſtand. And the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeeing the Conformiſts are at laſt, though to their own, Religion's, and the Nation's Expence, become ſo far enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as to ſee a neceſſity of growing more amicable towards them, and to enlarge the Terms of their Communion, grant an Indulgence to all Proteſtants that differ from them. And as we ought to admire the Wiſdom of God in thoſe Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences, by which Proteſtants are taught to lay aſide their Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſities, and to let fall their Perſecutions of one another; ſo it would be a Contradiction both to the Principles and repeated Proteſtations of Diſſenters, to aim at more than ſuch a Liberty as is conſiſtent with a National Eccleſiaſtick Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment. Yea it were to proclaim themſelves both Villains and Hypocrites, not to allow their Fellow-Proteſtants the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of their Judgments, with what further Profits and Emo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luments the Law will grant them, provided themſelves may be diſcharged from all obnoxiouſneſs to Penalties and Cenſures upon the account of their Conſciences, and be admitted a free and publick Practice of their own reſpective Modes of Diſcipline, and be ſuffered to worſhip God in thoſe ways which they think he hath required and enjoyned them. And were <hi>England</hi> immediately to be rendred ſo happy as to have a Proteſtant Prince or Princeſs (as we are not now quite out of hopes) aſcend the Throne, and to enjoy a Parliament duly choſen, and acting with freedom, no one Party of the Reformed Religion among us, muſt ever expect to be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed and ſupported to the denial of Liberty to others, much leſs to be by Law empowered to ruine and deſtroy them. Should it pleaſe Almighty God, to bring the Princeſs of <hi>Orange</hi> to the Crown, though the Church of <hi>England</hi> may in that caſe juſtly expect the being preſerved and upheld as the Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Eſtabliſhment, yet all other Proteſtants may very rationally promiſe themſelves an Indulgence, and that not only from the Mildneſs and compaſſionate Sweetneſs of her Temper, but
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:58012:17"/>from the Influence which the Prince her Husband will have upon her, who, as he is deſcended from Anceſtors, whoſe Glory it was to be the Redeemers of their Country from Papal Perſecution and Spaniſh Tyranny; ſo his Education, Genero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, Wiſdom, and many Heroick Vertues, diſpoſe him to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace all Proteſtants with an equal Tenderneſs, and to erect his Intereſt upon the being Head and Patron of all that profeſs the Reformed Religion. Had the late Duke of <hi>Monmouth</hi> been victorious againſt the Forces of the preſent King, and inabled to have wreſted the Scepter out of his Hand, though all Proteſtants might thereupon have expected, and would certainly have enjoyed an equal freedom, without the liable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of any Party to Penal Laws for matters of Religion, yet he would have been careful; and I have reaſon to believe that it was his purpoſe to have had the Church of <hi>England</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved and maintained, and that ſhe ſhould have ſuffered no alteration but what would have been to her Strength and Glory, through an enlargement of the Terms of her Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and what would have been to the Praiſe of her Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and Charity through her being perſwaded to bear with ſuch as differ from her in little things, and could not prevail with themſelves to partake with her in all Ordinances. Upon the whole, it is both the prudence and ſafety of Diſſenters, as they would eſcape Extirpation themſelves, and have Religion conveyed down to Poſterity, to unite their Strength and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to thoſe of the Church of <hi>England</hi> for the uphold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her againſt the aſſaults of Popiſh Enemies, who purſue her Subverſion. As matters have been circumſtanced and ſtated in <hi>England,</hi> there hath not been an Affront or Injury offered or done unto her by the Court, which did not at the ſame time reach and wound the Diſſenters. 'Tis not her being for Epiſcopacy, Ceremonies, and impoſed ſet-Forms of Worſhip, the Things about which ſhe and the Nonconformiſts differ, that ſhe hath been, not long ſince, maligned and ſtruck at by the Men in Power, and his Popiſh <hi>Juncto;</hi> but it is for being Proteſtant, Reformed, and Orthodox, Crimes under the Guilt whereof Diſſenters were equally concerned and involved. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therefore in oppoſition to the common Cauſe of Religion, that the late Court of Inquiſition was erected over her Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticks,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:58012:18"/>all Proteſtants jointly reſented the Wrongs which ſhe ſuſtain'd, and not only to ſympathize with thoſe dignified and lower Clergy which were called to ſuffer, but to eſpouſe her Quarrel with the ſame warmth that we would our own.</p>
            <p>And as we are to look upon thoſe of the Epiſcopal Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, to be the great Bulwark of the Proteſtant Religion and Reformed Intereſt in <hi>England;</hi> ſo it was farther incumbent on Diſſenters towards them, and a Duty which they owe to God, the Nation, and themſelves, not to be acceſſary to any thing, through which the legal Eſtabliſhment of the Church of <hi>England</hi> might have been, by any Act of pretended Regal Prerogative, weakned and ſupplanted.</p>
            <p>I never counſel the Diſſenters to renounce their Principles, nor to participate with the Prelatical Church in all Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, on the Terms to which they have ſtraitned and nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed their Communion. For while they remain unſatisfied of the lawfulneſs of thoſe Terms and Conditions, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not do it without offending God, and contracting Guilt upon their Souls; nor will they of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, Juſtice and Honeſty, expect it from them. For whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever any Man believeth to be Sin, it is ſo to him, and will by God be imputed as ſuch, till he be otherwiſe enlightned and convinced; nor are the Diſſenters to be falſe and cruel to themſelves, in order to be kind and friendly to them. But that which I would adviſe them unto is, that after the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the higheſt meaſure of Love to the conformable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations as Churches of Chriſt, and the eſteeming their Members as Chriſtian Proteſtant Brethren, notwithſtanding the ſeveral things wherein they judg them to err, and to be miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken, that they would not by any Act and Tranſaction of theirs, betray them into a Deſpotical Power, nor directly, nor indirectly acknowledg any Authority paramount unto, and ſuperceding the Laws, by which the Church of <hi>England</hi> is eſtabliſhed in its preſent Form, Order, and Mode of Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, Diſcipline and External Worſhip.</p>
            <p>Whatſoever Eaſe arrived to the Diſſenters, through the King's ſuſpending the Execution of the Penal Laws, without their Addreſs and Application, they might receive it with Joy and Humility in themſelves, and with Thankfulneſs to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:58012:18"/>God, nor was there hereby any prejudice offered on their part to the Authority of the Law, or Offence or Injury given or done to the conformable Clergy. Nor is it without grief and regret that the Church-Men have been forced to behold the haraſſing, ſpoiling, and impriſonment of the Nonconformiſts, while in the mean time the Papiſts were ſuffered to aſſemble to the Celebration of their Idolatrous Worſhip without Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and Controul. And had it been in their power to remedy it, and give Relief to their Proteſtant Brethren, they wou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d with delight and readineſs have embrac'd the occaſion and opportunity of doing it. But alas! inſtead of having an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage put into their hand, of contributing to the Relief of the Diſſenters, which I dare ſay, many of them ardently wiſh and deſire, they were compelled, contrary to their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination, as well as their Intereſt, to become inſtrumental in perſecuting and oppreſſing them. Nor does the late King covet a better and a more legal advantage againſt the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts, than that they would refuſe to purſue Diſſenters, and decline moleſting them with Eccleſiaſtical Cenſures and civil Puniſhments. So that their conditition was to be pitied and bewailed, in that they were hindred from acting againſt the Papiſts, though both enjoyned by Law, and influenced thereunto by Motives of ſelf-Preſervation, as well as by ties of Conſcience, while in the mean time they were forced to proſecute their fellow-Proteſtants, or elſe to be ſuſpended and depoſed, and put out of their Offices and Employs. And tho I believe that they would at laſt have more Peace in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and be better accepted with God in the great Day of their Account, ſhould they have refuſed to diſturb and proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute their Proteſtant Brethren, and ſoorn to be any longer Court-Tools for weakning and undermining the Reformed Cauſe and Intereſt, yet I could not but leave them to act in this as they ſhould be perſwaded in themſelves, and as they judged moſt agreeable to Principles of Wiſdom and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. In the interim, the Diſſenters have all the Reaſon in the World to believe, that the Proceedings of the Clergy and Members of the Church of <hi>England</hi> againſt them, were not the Reſults of their Election and Choice, but the Effects of moral Compulſion and Neceſſity. Nor will any Diſſenter
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:58012:19"/>that is prudent and diſcreet, blame them for a matter which they cannot help, but bear his Misfortune and Lot with Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience in himſelf, and with Compaſſion and Charity towards them; and have his Indignation raiſed only againſt that Court, which forced them to be inſtrumental in their Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion and Trouble. The Proteſtant Diſſenters could not be ſo far void of ſenſe, as to think that the Perſon lately in the Throne bore them any good-Will, but his drift was to ſcrue himſelf into a Supremacy and Abſoluteneſs over the Law, and to get ſuch an Authority confeſſed to be veſted in him, as when he pleaſed he might ſubvert the Eſtabliſhed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and ſet up Popery. For the ſame Power that he can diſpenſe with the Penal Statutes againſt the Nonconformiſts, he may alſo diſpenſe with thoſe againſt the Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks. And whoſoever owneth that he hath a Right to do the firſt, doth in effect own that he hath a Right to do the laſt. For if he be allowed a Power for the ſuperceding ſome Laws made in reference to Matters of Religion, he may challenge the like Power for the ſuperceding others of the ſame kind. And then by the ſame Authority that he can ſuſpend the Laws againſt Popery, he may alſo ſuſpend thoſe for Proteſtancy. And by the ſame Power that he can, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance of Law, indulge the Papiſts the Exerciſe of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in Houſes, he may eſtabliſh them in the publick Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of their Idolatry in Churches and Cathedrals. Yea, whereas the Laws that relate to Religion are enacted by no leſs Authority, than thoſe that are made for the Preſervation of our Civil Rights, ſhould the King be admitted to have an Arbitrary Power over the one, it is very like that by the Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick of <hi>White-hall</hi> he might have challeng'd the ſame Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luteneſs over the other. Nor do I doubt but that the <hi>eleven Judges,</hi> who gratified him with a Deſpoticalneſs over the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, would, when required, grant him the ſame over the latter, I know the Diſſenters have been under no ſmall Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, both by reaſon of being hindred from enjoying the Ordinances of the Goſpel, and becauſe of many grievous Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities which they ſuffer for their Nonconformity, of making Applications to the King for ſome Relief by his ſuſpending the Execution of the Laws; but they muſt give me leave to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:58012:19"/>add, that they ought not for the obtaining of a little Eaſe, to have betrayed the Kingdom, and ſacrifice the legal Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Government to the Luſt and Pleaſure of a Popiſh Prince, whom nothing leſs would ſerve than being Abſolute and Deſpotical. And had he once been in the quiet Poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of an Authority to diſpenſe with the Penal Laws, the Diſſenters would not long have enjoyed the benefit of it. Nor could they have denied him a Power of reviving the Execution of the Law, which is part of the Truſt depoſited with him as Supream Magiſtrate, who have granted him a Power of ſuſpending the Laws, which the Rules of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment precluded him from. And as he might whenſoever he pleaſed, cauſe the Laws, to which they were obnoxious, to be executed upon them, ſo by virtue of having an Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity acknowledged in him of ſuperceding the Laws, he might deprive them of the liberty of meeting together to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of five, a Grace which the Parliament thought fit to allow them, under all the other Severities to which they were ſubjected. Nor needs there any further Evidence, that the Princes challenging ſuch a Power was an Uſurpation, and that the Subjects making any Application, by which it ſeem'd allowed to him, was a betraying of the ancient legal Government of the Kingdom; whereas the moſt obſequious and ſervile Parliament to the Court that ever <hi>England</hi> knew, not only deny'd this Prerogative to the late King <hi>Charles,</hi> but made him renounce it by revoking his Declaration of Indulgence which he had emitted <hi>Anno</hi> 1672.</p>
            <p>And as it will be to the perpetual Honour of ſome of the Diſſenters to have choſen rather to ſuffer the Severities which the Laws make them liable unto, than by any Act and Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action of theirs, to undermine and weaken either the Church or the State; ſo it will be a means both of endearing them, we hope, not only to the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> now by a miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Providence brought in amongſt us, but to future Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and of bringing them and the Conformiſts into an union of Counſels and Endeavours againſt Popery and Tyranny for ever; which is at this ſeaſon a thing ſo indiſpenſably neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for their common preſervation. Eſpecially when though a new and more threatning Alliance and Confederacy with
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:58012:20"/>
               <hi>France,</hi> than that in 72, the King had not only engaged to act by and obſerve the ſame Meaſures towards Proteſtants in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> which that Monarch hath vouchſafed the World a Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern and Copy of in his carriage towards thoſe of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Religion in <hi>France:</hi> but had promiſed to diſturb the Peace and Repoſe of his Neighbours, and to commence a War, in conjunction with that Prince, againſt Foreign Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants. For as the King's giving Liberty and Protection to the <hi>Algerines</hi> to frequent his Havens, and ſell the Prizes which they take from the <hi>Dutch,</hi> is both a moſt infamous Action for a Prince, pretending to be a Chriſtian, and a direct violation of his Alliance with the <hi>States General;</hi> ſo nothing can be more evident, than that he thereby ſought to render them the weaker for him to aſſault, and that he was reſolved (if ſome unforeſeen and extraordinary Providence had not interpoſed and prevented) to declare War againſt them the next Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; in order whereunto great Remiſes of Mony were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ordered him from the French Court. So that the Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence which he pretends to be inclinable to afford the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, was not an effect of Kindneſs and Good-will, but an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifice whereby to oblige their Aſſiſtance in deſtroying thoſe Abroad of the ſame Religion with themſelves. Which if he could once compaſs, it were eaſy to foreſee what Fate both the Diſſenters, and they of the Communion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> were to expect. Who as they would not then have known whither to retreat for ſhelter; ſo they would have been deſtitute of Comfort in themſelves, and deprived of Pity from others; not only for having, through their Diviſions, made themſelves a Prey to the Papiſts at Home, but for having been acceſſary to the Ruin of the Reformed State Abroad; and which was the <hi>Aſilum</hi> and Sanctuary of all thoſe that were elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where oppreſſed and perſecuted for Religion.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Gloria Deo Optimo, Maximo.</l>
               <l>Honos Principi noſtri celciſſimo, pientiſſimo.</l>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:58012:20"/>
            <head>A Specimen of a Bill, For UNITING PROTESTANTS: BEING A rough Draught of ſuch Terms, as ſeem equal For the <hi>Conformiſt</hi> to grant, and the <hi>Non-conformist</hi> to yield to, for Peace ſake; Provided a good while, and Publiſhed on purpoſe only for the farther, better, and more eaſy Conſideration of the <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHereas, there are many Jealouſies riſen about <hi>Popery,</hi> which makes it even neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to the peace of the Nation, that the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Intereſt be united and ſtrengthened by all Good and Lawful Means: And to this end, there being this one proper Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient, <hi>to wit,</hi> The removing the Occaſion of Diviſions,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:58012:21"/>which ſeveral perſons do find to themſelves in thoſe late In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions, which yet were intended to the ſame purpoſe of Concord in the Nation: Be it Enacted, — That an Explanation of theſe Impoſitions, and ſuch Allevations, be allowed to the tenderly Conſiderate, and peaceably Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous, as follow.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity,</hi> By the <hi>Declaration of Aſſent and Conſent to all things, and every Thing contained in, and preſcribed by the two Books of Common-Prayer, and of Order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Priests and Deacons,</hi> we underſtand <note place="margin">Theſe Materials were provided, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Sitting of that <hi>Parliament</hi> which paſſed the <hi>Act of Uniformity,</hi> and other the like Rigorous Acts; and are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore drawn up in the form of an <hi>Expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natory Bill,</hi> becauſe it was ſuppoſed, they were not like to <hi>Repeal</hi> their own Acts, though they might be got to <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret</hi> them. But now we have a New <hi>Parliament,</hi> and that after another alſo Diſſolved, we may expect quicker Work: Yet will the Propoſing theſe Things ſtill to view, have their uſe, both for ſuppreſſing ſuch as have ſaid, The <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> know not what they would have; &amp; ſetting ſome Meaſure to our own deſires, and the <hi>Parliam.</hi> Condeſcentions about the ſame.</note> not, that theſe Books are in every Minute particular, infallible, or free from that Defect, which is incident to all Human Compoſure: But that they are in the main Contents, to be ſincerely approved and uſed. And we do therefore allow this Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be ſufficient, if it be made to the uſe of the Book, in the <hi>Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Conſtant Lords-Day-Service,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding any Exceptions ſome may have againſt ſome Things in the <hi>By-Offices,</hi> and <hi>Occaſional Service,</hi> the <hi>Rubrick,</hi> and otherwiſe. And for the Ceremonies which are made, and have been always, and on all hands, held to be only indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Things, we think ſit that they be left to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences and prudence of Miniſters, and People, every where (excepting the <hi>Cathedrals</hi>) to uſe them, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear them, as they judge it moſt meet for their own and others Edification: provided, that if any perſon will have his Child Baptiſed with the Sign of the <hi>Croſs,</hi> or ſtands upon any thing elſe, hitherto required by the Service-Book, if the Miniſter himſelf ſcruple the performance, he ſhall permit another to do it.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:58012:21"/>
            <p>In the ſame <hi>Act,</hi> By thoſe Words in the <hi>Subſcription,</hi> that <hi>It is not lawful to take Arms againſt the</hi> King, <hi>upon any Pretence whatſoever;</hi> we intend no new or ſtrange Thing, but the Right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Maintenance only of the <hi>King</hi>'s Authority againſt Rebellion,<note place="margin">That we have our Reaſon for theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations, any one may ſee that pleaſe in thoſe Arguments againſt the <hi>Oxford Oath,</hi> and this <hi>Subſcription</hi> which are offered in a little Book, Entituled, <hi>The Peaceable Deſign,</hi> ſo that we can by no means ſubmit thereto, without them. There is moreover this Clauſe [<hi>And I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to the</hi> Liturgy <hi>of the Church, as it is by Law Eſtabliſhed</hi>] we deſire may be ſpared, becauſe upon our Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration before of <hi>Aſſent</hi> and <hi>Conſent,</hi> (which must be the Bounds of our Senſe thereof) it is needleſs altogether, and can ſerve but for a Snare only to Mens Conſciences.</note> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the common determination of Learned Writers, in the Caſe of Subjection to Princes. By the Words, <hi>I abhor the Poſition of taking Arms by the Authority of the</hi> King, <hi>againſt any Commiſſionated by Him,</hi> we never thought of Advancing the Arbitrary Commiſſions of the <hi>King</hi> above Law; but by thoſe <hi>Commiſſionated by Him,</hi> we underſtand ſuch as are Legally Commiſſionated, and in the Legal purſuit of ſuch Commiſſion. By the Clauſe which follows, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires a Renunciation of all <hi>Endeavour of any Alteration of Government in the Church or State,</hi> we never meant to deny any Free-born Subject his Right, of Chooſing <hi>Parliament-Men,</hi> or Acting in his place for the Common Good any way, according to Law; but that he ſhall Renounce all ſuch <hi>Endeavour,</hi> as is Seditious, or not warranted by the Conſtitution of the Nation; and particularly, ſuch an <hi>Endeavour</hi> as was Aſſumed in the late Times, without, and againſt the Conſent of the <hi>King:</hi> And for the reſt of the <hi>Subſcription,</hi> which is enjoyned but to the Year 1682. Be it Enacted, that it ceaſe preſently, and be no longer en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned.</p>
            <p>And foraſmuch as there is an Oath preſcribed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of all <hi>Non-conformiſts</hi> Preachers, that reſide in any Corporate-Town, by a certain Act of the former <hi>Parliament,</hi> made at <hi>Oxford</hi> in the 17th Year of His now Majeſties Reign, Entituled, <hi>An Act for reſtraining</hi> Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:58012:22"/>
               <hi>from inhabiting Corporations:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">This <hi>Oath</hi> is of the ſame Contents with the <hi>Subſcription</hi> before; and to impoſe both, is nothing elſe but the multiplying Wrath, and laying Lead on the already Laden.</note> We do further declare, That it ſhall ſuffice any Man, for the Enjoyment of his Free-born Liberty, of Inhabiting where he thinks beſt; and ſerve him alſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of the fore-mentioned <hi>Subſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> to take that <hi>Oath</hi> in this form of Words following. I. A. B. <hi>do ſwear, That I hold it unlawful upon any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, to take Arms againſt the</hi> King, <hi>His Government or Laws: And that I diſclaim that dangerous Poſition, of taking Arms by his Authority, againſt His Perſon, or any Legally Commiſſionated by him, in the Legal purſuit of ſuch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions: And that I will not endeavour any Alteration of Government in the Church or State, in any way or manner, not warranted by the Conſtitution of the Kingdom, or any otherwiſe than by Act of Parliament.</hi> And as ſoon as any Man hath taken the <hi>Oath</hi> thus, he ſhall be diſcharged of all penalty for his omiſſion before.</p>
            <p>We do declare moreover, That whereas it is required alſo in the <hi>Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity,</hi> that every Miniſter who injoys any Living or Eccleſiaſtical preferment, ſhall be Ordained by a Biſhop; and there are ſeveral perſons of late, who in caſe of Neceſſity, for want of Biſhops took <hi>Preſbyterian-Orders:</hi> Our meaning is not in any wiſe to diſguſt the Reformed Churches beyond the Seas, and make it neceſſary for ſuch to be Re-ordained to the Office; but that they receive this Second impoſition of Hands to the Exerciſe of their Office in the new charge,<note place="margin">There is <hi>Reordinatio ad Officium,</hi> which (we ſay) is generally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryed by Divines: <hi>Re-ordinatio ad Exercitium particulate,</hi> which may be irrefragably proved from <hi>Acts 13.2, 3.</hi> with <hi>Acts 14.26.</hi> amd conſequently allow'd to ſerve this Occaſion.</note> unto which they are, or ſhall be called; and that the Biſhop ſhall frame his Words accordingly.</p>
            <p>And whereas there is a Subſcription alſo in the <hi>Canons,</hi> and the <hi>Canonical-Oath</hi> of <hi>Obedience,</hi> impoſed on moſt Miniſters by the Biſhops, that have given ſome of the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:58012:22"/>greateſt Occaſion to <hi>Non-conformity</hi> heretofore; which yet never paſſed into Law by any Act of <hi>Parliament:</hi> We do further declare,<note place="margin">If the <hi>Oaths</hi> of <hi>Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> and <hi>Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> be taken and the <hi>Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> of the Church ſubſcribed, and the <hi>Declaration</hi> before to the Common Prayer, made; we ſee no need of boyling over theſe three Things again for us, in the Canons.</note> That nothing more of that kind ſhall be required of Miniſters henceforward, then was made and held neceſſary by the Act of the <hi>thirteenth of Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in regard there hath been great Offence taken by Conſcientious Miniſters, at the Biſhops, (or their Courts) commanding them to read the Sentence of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication againſt ſome or other of their Pariſh,<note place="margin">Neither ſhall any Miniſter be puniſhable for the withhold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his own Act in delivery of either Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to any, who in his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience he judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es unworthy, or uncapable of it. As we think there is no <hi>Elder</hi> in the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> who is not a <hi>Paſtor,</hi> and that there is no <hi>Lay Paſtor;</hi> ſo do we account, that there is no Paſtor or Presbyter, but ſuch as have the power both to <hi>Rule</hi> and <hi>Teach,</hi> committed to them, by Christ: Yet do we, for all that, apprehend it not only <hi>Lawful,</hi> but <hi>Expedient,</hi> for the ordinary Miniſters of our <hi>Parochial</hi> Congregations, (when the Church is <hi>Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal</hi>) to commit part of their charge, (to wit that of Ruling) <hi>in Actu Secundo,</hi> to ſome few among them, who are more Eminently fitted for the Work, (that is, the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) and conſequently to the Biſhop: So that, if this Fundamental Right of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning their own Flocks, be but acknowledged to Reſide in every Presbyter, by granting ſo much to us as this (and what hath preceded) comes to, we ſhall be unwilling to fall off from <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> upon the points of <hi>Ordination</hi> and <hi>Juriſdiction.</hi>
               </note> for ſuch faults as they think not at all worthy of ſo great a Cenſure: We declare it but a juſt Thing, that every Miniſter be firſt ſatisfyed in the Cauſe, or elſe be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from the Execution of that Charge; and that the Biſhop (or his Court) provide ſome other perſon that is ſatisfyed about it, to do it.</p>
            <p>And to the intent, that a free ſearch after Truth may not be diſcouraged in the purſuit of Concord, and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Scruples avoided upon that Account: We declare, that though an <hi>Authentick</hi> Interpretation be required, as to the Subſtance of all Laws, yet in the Articles of the <hi>Church,</hi> which are <hi>Theſes</hi> for Agreement, and not Laws) and the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies,</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:58012:23"/>a <hi>Doctrinal</hi> Interpretation ſhall be held ſufficient for an <hi>Aſſent</hi> or <hi>Subſcription</hi> to them.<note place="margin">The <hi>Authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick</hi> Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, is the meaning of the Major Part of the <hi>Convocation:</hi> A <hi>Doctrinal</hi> Interpretation, is the meaning of any one of the <hi>Doctors</hi> there preſent, (and conſequently of any other Learned <hi>Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi>) who are ſuppoſed to have the Liberty to abound in their own Senſe, ſo long as they can agree in the Words of the <hi>Article</hi> Eſtabliſhed. And this Clauſe therefore we put in upon Mature Conſideration, in regard more eſpecially to the <hi>Conſcientious Latitudinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> (which is a Name abuſed) who being ſome <hi>Arminian,</hi> and ſome <hi>Calvinian,</hi> cannot otherwiſe Subſcribe the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the ſame <hi>Theſes,</hi> as the <hi>Reader</hi> may ſee more in ſuch a ſort of Book as this, called <hi>The Healing Paper,</hi> out of which this <hi>Bill for Union</hi> is Collected.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And becauſe the very Superintendency of Biſhops, and that Subjection to them which is required by the Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Realm, is, or may be an hinderance to many ſober Miniſters, and other Proteſtants, of coming into the Church, who are ready to conſent to the Doctrine, but not to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline or Government of it: We do declare, That ſo long as any perſon or party do acknowledge the <hi>King's Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy,</hi> as <hi>Head</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> in this Nation, and obey their Ordinary, or the Biſhops, <hi>in Licitis &amp; Honeſtis,</hi> upon the Account of his Authority (committed to them for the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of that External Regiment <hi>Circa Sacra</hi> which is gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by all our Divines,<note place="margin">That is, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though there be ſome that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge our <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſan Prelates</hi> to be Chriſts Officers, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from the Elders in ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, yet ſo long as they can live Peaceable lives in Obedience to them, as Eccleſiastical Magiſtrates under His Majeſty, for the keeping the ſeveral Congregations in their Precincts, <hi>to that Goſpel Order, which themſelves allow, and for ſuper-viſing their Conſtitutions in Things indifferent, that nothing be done, but in Subordination to the Peace of the Kingdom,</hi> (which is a Notion wherein the Judicious of every Party may acquieſce, and expreſſed by us in theſe very Words in a Book forenamed) it is ſufficient unto National Church-<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion.</note> to the Higher Powers in every Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,) it is enough for the owning <hi>Epiſcopal Juriſdiction</hi> (ſo far as they do own it, in the Declaration of <hi>Aſſent</hi> and <hi>Conſent,</hi> or in any other part of <hi>Conformity;</hi>) and ſhall ſerve them to all intents and purpoſes in Law, no leſs than a profeſſed belief and acknowledgment of the immediate Divine Right of it.</p>
            <p>Be it therefore Enacted by this preſent <hi>Parliament,</hi> That i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> any Perſon be willing to Conform to the preſent Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:58012:23"/>of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> and her Service appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted according to theſe Explanations, Alleviations, Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, Lenitives, or Cautions, he ſhall be admitted to any Eccleſiaſtical Preferment, and enjoy the uſe of his Miniſtry without any moleſtation: All Statutes, Canons, or Laws to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>And for the making this Act of better Signification to the Concerned, and the prevention of that Scandal which is raiſed on the Clergy, through the Covetouſneſs of ſome, in heaping up to themſelves all the Preferments they can get, when others have ſcarce Subſiſtance for their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, and the Souls of many people are thereby neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: Be it farther Enacted, That no Clergy-man for the Three next years enſuing,<note place="margin">We propoſe theſe Things, we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, as if we were in <hi>Republica Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonis,</hi> but we ſhould be glad to ſee any Fruits of this kind, as thoſe who are in <hi>Faece Romuli</hi> may expect. What is Right and Juſt, and ought to be done, is one thing, and to be ſought; though what is like to be done, or will be done, is another.</note> be ſuffered to Enjoy any more than one Living or Cure of Souls, and one Dignity, (or other Eccleſiaſtical preferment) at one Time; and that every Man (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Exception) that hath more than One of Either, ſhall immediately give up the Reſt to be diſtributed among thoſe who ſhall be brought off from their <hi>Non-conformity,</hi> upon the Terms of this <hi>Act</hi> into the Eſtabliſhed Order. Which that they may alſo be obtained, and poſſeſſed with a clean Conſcience, and that grievous Corruption of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony</hi> may be extripate out of the Land: Be it Enacted moreover, That every Patron that ſhall henceforward pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent his Clerk to any Living, ſhall have the Oath called <hi>The Simonical Oath,</hi> impoſed on himſelf, no leſs than on the Incumbent: And if he Refuſes to take it, that then the Biſhop ſhall have immediate Power (taking only the ſame Oath) of Preſentation in his Room.</p>
            <p>And foraſmuch, as there are ſome Miniſters of a good Life, that cannot (according to their Judgments) allow of our Parochial Churches, nor a Book of <hi>Liturgy:</hi> But do chooſe to Worſhip God, and Jeſus Chriſt, in the way of their gathered or ſeparate Congregations; and crave the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:58012:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>Protection and Clemency of the <hi>King,</hi> upon their Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, as other Subjects: Be it finally Enacted, for the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs and quiet of the Realm, and the Reduction of theſe Men by other means than thoſe which have hitherto proved unſucceſsful, That every Chriſtian Subject throughout the Land that profeſs the Reformed Religion, and be not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vict of <hi>Popery,</hi> be pardoned all Faults and Penalties, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred upon the account of any Fore-paſſed <hi>Non-confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity;</hi> and that they ſhall not, during theſe Seven Years next enſuing, be proſecuted upon any Penal Law for their Conſciences, in the matter of Religion; They carrying themſelves innocently and peaceably, with ſubmiſſion to the Civil, and without diſturbance to the Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Government, now ſetled in the Nation: All Statutes to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
            <note place="margin">There are two Parts of this Bill; One for <hi>Concord</hi> or <hi>Coalition</hi> with all ſuch as can joyn in Parochi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Communion, in the Clauſes before: The other for <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance</hi> of thoſe that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, in this laſt Clauſe. For, what ſhall we do with ſuch? We muſt not knock them on the Head: They muſt therefore have time. If the <hi>Parliament</hi> will begin with the laſt firſt, that is, a Suſpenſion of the Penal Statutes, and then let us treat for a Compoſition after, we conſent with all ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Hearts, and like the Method beſt. <hi>Then</hi> Abner <hi>called unto</hi> Joab, <hi>and ſaid, Shall the Swor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> devour for ever! Knoweſt thou not, that it will be bitterneſs in the end! How long ſhall it be, ere thou bid the People return from following of their Brethren.</hi>
            </note>
            <note n="*" place="margin">
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntil by a further Act of <hi>Parliament,</hi> or a Convocation, thoſe that are fit to be Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and the Intolerable be-diſtinguiſhed.</note>
            <div type="proposal">
               <head>In Short,</head>
               <p>A Repeal of our Laws about <hi>Conformity</hi> unto the 13th of <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> Or, a New <hi>Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity;</hi> Or, The <hi>Kings</hi> Declaration concerning Eccleſiaſtical Affairs at His firſt coming in, turned into a Law, were <hi>Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His latter Declaration to all his Loving Subjects (ſome few things in both, yet a little conſidered) made ſo, were <hi>Indulgence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Bill for <hi>Comprehenſion</hi> with <hi>Indulgence,</hi> both together, will do our buſineſs. An Addition, or Clauſe in it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Pluralities,</hi> will do it with Supererrogation.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>Deo Gloria.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
